  <chapter id="Installation">
    <title>
      Installation and Invocation
    </title>
    <sect1 id="RequiredEnv">
      <title>
	Required Environment
      </title>
      <para>
	&SISC; primarily targets the Java Virtual
	Machine, and the Java v1.2 and higher class libraries.  The
	1.2 libraries and VM are required due to a reliance on memory
	reference functionality used to properly garbage collect
	unused symbols while still maintaining pointer equality between
	those that remain active.
      </para>
      <para>
	&SISC; does not require any particular operating system, though
	the official distribution currently provides launching
	assistance for Windows and Unix based systems.  Theoretically
	any machine that supports Java 1.2 or higher should be able to
	run &SISC;.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="REPL">
      <title>
	The Read-Eval-Print-Loop
      </title>
      <para>
	As in most Scheme systems, &SISC;'s primary
	human interface is a REPL, or Read-Eval-Print-Loop.  &SISC;
	presents the user with a prompt ('>'), then reads an
	s-expression from the console.  &SISC; then evaluates the
	s-expression, producing a value or error, which it then
	prints.  Finally a prompt is displayed and the process begins
	again.
      </para>
      <para>
	The process terminates with a forced kill of the JVM (with
	Control-C or similar), or when an end of file is detected on
	the console.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="DisplayConventions">
      <title> 
	Display Conventions
      </title>
      <para>
	Executing or loading code in the REPL ordinarily produces a value
	result which is displayed during the Print phase.  However,
	two other message types may be displayed.  First, if an error
	is raised that is not handled by the running program, the
	message will be described in one of three forms:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
	Error: &lt;description&gt;

	Error in &lt;error-location&gt;: &lt;description&gt;

	Error.
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	The first form describes an error that was raised in an
	anonymous procedure or syntax.  The second describes an error
	that was raised in a named procedure or syntax definition.
	The error-location indicates which procedure encountered
	the error.  The final form is produced by an explicit call
	to the error function with no arguments.
      </para>
      <para>
	In addition to errors, it is possible for code to produce
	warnings during compilation or run-time.  A warning is a
	message to the user about a condition that is unusual but not
	terminal to the program flow.  The compiler, for example, does
	a minimal amount of sanity checking on code and may produce
	warnings about code that has the potential to raise errors
	during execution.  Warnings are always distinguished from
	ordinary messages by surrounding braces ({}). 
      </para>
      <programlisting>
	{warning: &lt;description&gt;}
      </programlisting>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
sgml-parent-document:("sss.xml" "chapter")
End:
-->
