  <chapter>
    <title>
      Introduction
    </title>
    <para>
      &SISC; is a lightweight, platform independent
      Scheme system whose primary goals are rapid execution of the
      complete &R5RS; and future Scheme
      standards, plus a useful superset for real-world application
      development. 
    </para>
    <para>
      &SISC;'s development progresses in two
      directions, to improve the core interpreter to be simpler,
      more elegant, and more efficient; and to add necessary
      functionality through extensions that do not complicate the
      core.
    </para>
    <sect1 id="Features">
      <title>
	Features
      </title>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Full &R5RS; compliance
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Efficient number tower, with support for integers, floating-point numbers, rationals, and complex numbers of arbitrary precision
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Lightweight Scheme engine, requiring less than 200 kilobytes of code.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Runtime extensiblity through a scopeable module system, which may add new functions and first-class types.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="About">
      <title>
	About this document
      </title>
      <para>
	This document explains the &SISC; Scheme system. It assumes
	knowledge of the Scheme language. As such, when discussing the
	Scheme language, we will focus primarily on differences
	between the Scheme standard and the language implemented by
	&SISC;.
      </para>
      <para>
	Secondly, &SISC; implements the &R5RS; standard. As such, any
	code written to that standard should run without reading any
	further.
      </para>
      <sect2 id="AboutProcedures">
	<title>
	  About procedure documentation
	</title>
	<para>
	  Throughout this document, procedures will be defined using
	  the following syntax:
	</para>
	  <para>
	    
	  <funcsynopsis>
	    <funcprototype>
	      <funcdef><function>max</function></funcdef>
	      <paramdef><parameter>string</parameter></paramdef>
	      <paramdef><parameter>string</parameter></paramdef>
	    </funcprototype>
	  </funcsynopsis>

	</para>
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
	    Description of the procedure's semantics.
	  </para>
	</blockquote>
	<programlisting>
	  &parameter; (parameter-name [new-value])
	  Description of the parameter and its effects.
	   
	   
	  &syntax; (syntactic-keyword structure ...)
	  Description of the syntax expressions semantics
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  A procedure is a function that takes a number of arguments
	  and produces a result, which may be undefined. The arguments
	  of a procedure are always evaluated before the procedure is
	  invoked.</para> 
	<para>
	  A parameter is a value that effects the operation of part of
	  the Scheme system. When a parameter is invoked with no
	  arguments, the current value of the parameter is
	  returned. With arguments, the value of the parameter is
	  changed to the arguments given. 
	</para>
	<para>
	  Finally, syntax is any construct whose arguments are not
	  necessarily other s-expressions. Arguments to a syntactic
	  expression are not necessarily evaluated. Syntactic
	  expressions are expanded at compile time to expressions that
	  have the correct semantics but contain no additional
	  syntactic expressions, and are often much more difficult to
	  read then the unexpanded version.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Procedures, parameters, and syntax may take one or more
	  arguments.  The name of an argument in a description
	  indicates the expected type of the argument.  'value'
	  indicates any type.  If the argument is enclosed in square
	  brackets ([]), that parameter is optional, and may be
	  ommitted.  If the description ends in ellipses (...), then 
	  additional arguments may be provided, but are not required.
	</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
sgml-parent-document:("sss.xml" "chapter")
End:
-->
