  <chapter id="LibraryFunctions">
    <title>
      &SISC; Library Functions
    </title>
    <sect1 id="Debugging">
      <title>
	Debugging
      </title>
      <para>
	&SISC; provides debugging aids that can be added to Scheme
	source code, as well as limited support for debugging without
	modification. 
      </para>
      <programlisting>
	&syntax; (trace-lambda trace-name formals body)

	When replaced with a trace-lambda, all calls to a lambda defined 
	procedure are traced on the console.  <emphasis>trace-name</emphasis> 
	is a symbol to identify the procedure in the trace. 
	<emphasis>formals </emphasis>and <emphasis>body</emphasis> have
	identical semantics to lambda.
	 
	&syntax; (trace-let loop-name formal-bindings body)
	Replaces a named-let expression in a similar manner to trace-lambda.  
	 
	&procedure; (trace-top-level-procedures symbol ...)
	&returns; undefined
	 
	Begins traces on the procedures named by the symbols given.  The procedures must be defined in the top-level environment.
	 
	&procedure; (untrace-top-level-procedures symbol ...)
	&returns; undefined
	 
	Stops tracing the top-level procedures named by the symbols given.
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	Trace-lambda and trace-let are useful for debugging anonymous
	lambdas and named-lets
	respectively. Trace-top-level-procedures can be used to trace
	calls to any procedure, including native procedures and stored
	continuations.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="BitwiseLogicalOperations">
      <title>
	Bitwise Logical Operations
      </title>
      <para>
	In addition to the &R5RS; set of procedures that deal with
	numbers, &SISC; provides operators for performing bitwise
	logic operations on a limited range of integers.  The domain of the
	logical operators are exact real integers of the range
	-2,147,483,647 to 2,147,483,646 inclusive.  An error is raised
	if the logical operators are applied to integers outside this
	range, to a non-integer, or a non-real.
      </para>
      <programlisting>
	&procedure; (logand integer [integer] ...)
	&returns; The logical AND of all provided operands
	
	&procedure; (logor integer [integer] ...)
	&returns; The logical OR of all provided operands

	&procedure; (logxor integer [integer] ...)
	&returns; The logical exclusive-OR of all provided operands

	&procedure; (lognot integer)
	&returns; The logical NOT of the provided operand
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	In addition, two operators are provided to perform arithmetic
	shifts on any integer (these operators do not have the range
	limitation the previous logical functions do).  The shift
	operators return a newly generated number formed by shifting
	the provided number left or right by the given number of bits.
      </para>
      <programlisting>
	&procedure; (ashl integer bits)
	&returns; <emphasis>integer</emphasis> shifted left by <emphasis>bits</emphasis> bits.

	&procedure; (ashr integer bits)
	&returns; <emphasis>integer</emphasis> shifted right by <emphasis>bits</emphasis> bits.
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	Mathematically, if r is the number, and s is the number of
	bits, ashl calculates:
	<programlisting>
	  r x 2<superscript>s</superscript>
	</programlisting>
	while ashr calculates
	<programlisting>
	  r / 2<superscript>s</superscript>
	</programlisting>
	in the integer domain.  Both ashl and ashr operate on exact
	integers and produce only exact integers.  
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="OperatingSystemInterface">
      <title>
	Operating System interface
      </title>
      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
sgml-parent-document:("sss.xml" "chapter")
End:
-->
