<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      SISC is a lightweight, platform independent interpreter of the
      algorithmic language 
      <ulink url="http://schemers.org">Scheme</ulink>.  The goal of
      the SISC interpreter is to create a runtime for Scheme that is a
      correct and complete implementation of the R5RS Scheme standard,
      and all future standards, as well as provide a useful set of
      extensions for real-world programming.  
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Features</title>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>Full R5RS compliance with no exceptions</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  Efficient number tower, with arbitrary precision integers,
	  rationals, and floating point and complex numbers.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  Lightweight Scheme engine, requiring less than 200k of 
	  code.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  Extensibility through runtime-loadable modules, which may
	  add new functions and first-class types.
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Architecture</title>
      <para>
	SISC's architecture is broken up into four conceptual
	components: the Runtime, Compiler, Engine, and Modules.</para>
      <para>
	The Runtime is a purely conceptual component, which simply
	consists of a platform independent Runtime on which SISC is
	built.  At the time of this writing, only a single Runtime,
	the Java Virtual Machine, is supported.
      </para>
      <para>
	The Compiler contains of the parser and lexer, an analyzer,
	and optionally a compiler. The parser and lexer turn unicode 
	text representing Scheme code and Data into Scheme
	s-expressions.  Then, the analyzer turns the s-expressions
	into an intermediate form called SISC Expressions.  If
	present, a compiler may then take the SISC Expressions and
	generate runtime bytecode.  Currently no compiler exists.
      </para>
      <para>
	The Engine drives the evaluation of Scheme programs, by
	providing a register set, a set of environments, and an
	execution model (implemented as an Object Oriented hierarchy
	of Expressions).  It is the design of an engine that operates
	on the intermediate Expressions that provides efficient
	interpretation of Scheme code with support for first-class
	continuations.
      </para>
      <para>
	Finally, Modules extend the Engine to implement the Scheme
	builtin functions described in the Scheme standard that cannot
	be written in terms of other Scheme code, or code that
	benefits by running natively on the Runtime.
      </para>
	</section>
  </chapter>
  

